Guide to the Cased Image File 1840-ongoing PR 12
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Cased Image File
1840-Ongoing
PR 12
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
42.0 Linear feet
The Cased Image File at New-York Historical Society is predominantly made up of Daguerreotypes, Ambrotypes and Tintypes. Portraits constitute most of the file, and many items are still in the cases in which they were sold. The file also contains other non-paper photographic formats such as Opalotypes and framed transparencies.
Access to Collection
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Provenance
The collection's accession dates span from 1873 to the present, but the majority was accessioned between 1930 and 1960.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Arrangement note
The Cased Images are organized by medium and size. There are six medium categories. Multiple Media inlcudes cases which hold both an Ambrotype and a Tintype, for example. Other Media include Transparency, Hallotype, Opalotype, and Autochrome. Cases refers to either a case missing an image or to a part of a case, such as a mat, edge preserver or lining. For the most part, everything is cataloged on an item level (except for groupings of unidentified Tintypes and in instances where several items are held in one case). Item-level descriptions are provided in the container list by number of image. To identify the box number for a particular image, consult the list below.
Series I: Ambrotypes
Box: 1 Ambrotypes, 1 - 49
Box: 2 Ambrotypes, 50 - 80
Box: 3 Ambrotypes, 81 - 108
Box: 4 Ambrotypes, 109-131
Box: 5 Ambrotypes, 132 - 173
Box: 6 Ambrotypes, 174 - 197
Box: 7 Ambrotypes, 198 - 221
Box: 8 Ambrotypes, 222 - 245
Box: 9 Ambrotypes, 246 - 267
Box: 10 Ambrotypes, 268 - 289
Box: 11 Ambrotypes, 290 - 311
Box: 12 Ambrotypes, 312 - 332
Box: 13 Ambrotypes, 333 - 352
Box: 14 Ambrotypes, 353 - 373
Box: 15 Ambrotypes, 374 - 390
Box: 16 Ambrotypes, 391 - 404
Box: 17 Ambrotypes, 405 - 414
Box: 18 Ambrotypes, 415 - 419
Box: 19 Ambrotypes, 420
Box: 47 (oversize) Ambrotypes, 421
Series II: Daguerrotypes
Box: 20 Daguerrotypes, 1 - 27
Box: 21 Daguerrotypes, 28 - 59
Box: 22 Daguerrotypes, 60 - 89
Box: 23 Daguerrotypes, 90 - 115
Box: 24 Daguerrotypes, 116 - 141
Box: 25 Daguerrotypes, 142 - 189
Box: 26 Daguerrotypes, 190 - 215
Box: 27 Daguerrotypes, 216 - 240
Box: 28 Daguerrotypes, 241 - 265
Box: 29 Daguerrotypes, 266 - 289
Box: 30 Daguerrotypes, 290 - 314
Box: 31 Daguerrotypes, 315 - 340
Box: 32 Daguerrotypes, 341 - 364
Box: 33 Daguerrotypes, 365 - 388
Box: 34 Daguerrotypes, 389 - 410
Box: 35 Daguerrotypes, 411 - 434
Box: 36 Daguerrotypes, 435 - 458
Box: 37 Daguerrotypes, 459 - 482
Box: 38 Daguerrotypes, 483 - 506
Box: 39 Daguerrotypes, 507 - 528
Box: 40 Daguerrotypes, 529 - 550
Box: 41 Daguerrotypes, 551 - 573
Box: 42 Daguerrotypes, 574 - 592
Box: 43 Daguerrotypes, 592.1 - 616
Box: 44 Daguerrotypes, 617 - 632
Box: 49 Daguerrotypes, 633 - 651
Box: 50 Daguerrotypes, 652 - 670
Box: 51 Daguerrotypes, 671 - 689
Box: 52 Daguerrotypes, 690 - 707
Box: 53 Daguerrotypes, 708 - 725
Box: 54 Daguerrotypes, 726 - 743
Box: 55 Daguerrotypes, 744 - 757
Box: 56 Daguerrotypes, 758 - 772
Box: 57 Daguerrotypes, 773 - 783
Box: 58 Daguerrotypes, 784 - 794.1
Box: 59 Daguerrotypes, 795 - 805
Box: 60 Daguerrotypes, 806 - 816
Box: 61 Daguerrotypes, 817 - 826
Box: 62 Daguerrotypes, 827 - 837
Box: 63 Daguerrotypes, 838 - 849
Box: 64 Daguerrotypes, 850 - 858
Box: 65 Daguerrotypes, 859 - 867
Box: 66 Daguerrotypes, 868 - 877
Box: 67 Daguerrotypes, 878 - 882
Box: 68 Daguerrotypes, 883
Box: 48 oversize Daguerrotypes, 884
Box: 68A Daguerrotypes, 885-894
Series III: Tintypes
Box: 69 Tintypes, 1 - 79
Box: 70 Tintypes, 80 - 134
Box: 71 Tintypes, 135 - 174
Box: 72 Tintypes, 175 - 249
Box: 73 Tintypes, 250 - 309
Box: 74 Tintypes, 310 - 324
Box: 75 Tintypes, 325 - 414
Box: 76 Tintypes, 415 - 484
Box: 77 Tintypes, 485 - 524
Box: 78 Tintypes, 525 - 559
Box: 79 Tintypes, 560 - 594
Box: 80 Tintypes, 595 - 607
Box: 81 Tintypes, 608 - 613
Box: 81A Tintypes, 614-653
Series IV: Multiple Media
Box: 82 Multiple Media, 1 - 12
Series V: Other Media
Box: 83 Other Media, 1 - 15
Box: 84 Other Media, 16 - 30
Box: 85 Other Media, 31 - 40
Box: 86 Other Media, 41 - 44
Box: 87 Other Media, 45 - 51
Box: 46 oversize Other Media, 52
Box: 45 oversize Other Media, 53
Series VI: Cases
Box: 88 Cases, 1 - 10
Box: 89 Cases, 11 - 12
Box: 90 Cases, 13 - 16
Historical Note
Louis-Jacques-Mandé Daguerre invented the daguerreotype process in France. The invention was announced to the public on August 19, 1839 at a meeting of the French Academy of Sciences in Paris. American photographers quickly capitalized on this new invention, which was capable of capturing a "truthful likeness." Daguerreotypists in major cities invited celebrities and political figures to their studios in the hopes of obtaining a likeness for display in their windows and reception areas. They encouraged the public to visit their galleries, which were like museums, in the hope that they would desire to be photographed as well. By 1850, there were over 70 daguerreotype studios in New York City alone. The popularity of the daguerreotype declined in the late 1850s when the ambrotype, a faster and less expensive photographic process, became available. A few contemporary photographers have revived the process.
Ambrotypes were made from the 1850s and up to the late eighties, the process having been invented by Frederick Scott Archer in collaboration with Peter Fry, a colleague. Ambrotypes are direct positives, made by under-exposing a collodion negative, bleaching it, and then placing a black background - usually black velvet - behind it. Though they slightly resemble Daguerreotypes, the method of production was very different, and Ambrotypes were much cheaper. Ambrotypes became very popular, particularly in America.
Another variant of the Ambrotype is the Tintype process. The tintype, also known as a ferrotype, is produced on metallic sheet (not, actually, tin) instead of glass. The plate was coated with collodion and sensitized just before use, as in the wet plate process. It was introduced by Adolphe Alexandre Martin in 1853, and became instantly popular, particularly in the United States. The most common size was about the same as the carte-de-visite, 2 1/4'' x 3 1/2'', but both larger and smaller ferrotypes were made. The smallest are called "gem" tintypes, about the size of a postage-stamp, made simultaneously on a single plate in a camera with 12 or 16 lenses. They were often made by unskilled photographers, and their quality was very variable. They do have some significance, however, in that they made photography available to working classes, not just to the more well-to-do. Whereas up till then the taking of a portrait had been more of a special "event" from the introduction of tintypes, we see more relaxed, spontaneous poses, as well as more outdoor scenes.
Scope and Contents Note
The Cased Image File consists of 2,301 items. 435 of these are Ambrotypes, 893 are Daguerreotypes, and 801 are Tintypes. Though most of these images are housed in their original leather cases, the collection also contains 87 Union Cases. The remaining 172 items are primarily mixed media, Opalotypes and empty cases or case remnants. The collection fills approximately 90 boxes (or approx. 42 linear feet).
The collection is predominantly made up of Daguerreotypes, Ambrotypes and Tintypes. Portraits constitute most of the file, and many items are still in the cases in which they were sold. The file also contains other non-paper photographic formats such as Opalotypes and framed transparencies. Heavily represented family groups include the Harper, Webb, Kellogg-Comstock, MacMartin-MacLaren, Eames, Ward, Hincken, Stuyvesant, Greenwood and Ellis families and associates. Such prominent persons as Henry Clay, Abraham Lincoln, Peter Cooper, Asher B. Durand, Millard Fillmore, Washington Irving, Jenny Lind, John McComb, William H. Seward and Daniel Webster appear in the Cased Images Collection. Other striking images include Caesar, a New York slave; the 1856 Rutgers Female Institute graduating class, and several stereographic daguerreotypes by J. F. Mascher of Philadelphia and Samuel F.B. Morse, as well occupational portraits of firemen, barbers and actors. Among the views are an interior of the New York Crystal Palace in the 1850s and a Niagara Falls landscape. Most of the photographers represented in the collection operated in New York City, for example: Rufus Anson, Abraham Bogardus, Mathew Brady, Charles D. Fredericks, Jeremiah Gurney, L. Cathan, Silas A. Holmes and John Plumbe. The collection also contains an image made by 20th Century daguerreotypist Robert Shlaer. Two images created by Jerry Spagnoli were removed in May 2002 and now comprise part of the Jerry Spagnoli Photograph Collection.
Although a few of the images are reproductions of paintings made at earlier dates, and a large number of the images are completely undated, it is clear from the labeled and identified items that the majority were taken between 1850 and 1870, with many images taken early as the 1850's.
Anson, Rufus; Beekman family; Bogardus, A. (Abraham), 1822-1908; Brady, Mathew B., 1823 (ca.)- 1896; Cathan, L.; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852 -- Portraits; Comstock family; Cooper family; Cooper, Peter, 1791-1883--Portraits; Crystal Palace (New York, N.Y.); De Groot family; Delano family; Durand, Asher Brown, 1796-1886--Portraits; Eames family; Ellis family; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874--Portraits; Fredricks, Charles DeForest, 1823-1894; Greenwood family; Gurney, Jeremiah, 1812-1895; Harper family; Hewitt family; Hewitt, Abram S. (Abram Stevens), 1822-1903--Portraits; Hincken family; Holmes, S. A. (Silas A.), 1819 or 20-1886; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859--Portraits; Kellogg family; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Portraits; Lind, Jenny, 1820-1887--Portraits; MacLaren family; MacMartin family; Mascher, J. F.; McComb, John, 1763-1853--Portraits; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Plumbe, John, 1809-1857; Rogers family; Schermerhorn family; Schuyler family; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872--Portraits; Shlaer, Robert; Stuyvesant family; Thursby family; Thursby, Emma Cecilia, 1845-1931--Portraits; Ward family; We family; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852 -- Portraits; Actors -- United States -- Portraits; Ambrotypes; Barbers--United States--Portraits; Cased photographs; Daguerreotypes; Fire fighters--United States--Portraits; Group portraits; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.); Opalotypes; Photographic prints; Portraits; Soldiers--United States--Portraits; Tintypes
- Series I: Ambrotype, 1
  General Note
  Where identified, the photographer's name appears in brackets after the image title.
  To locate the box number of a particular image, consult the list in the Arrangement note.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-1)
    General note
    Female figure, front view, wearing plaid dress with white scalloped collar, brooch, curly hair to shoulders, bust.
  - Unidentified Male (Item 1-2)
    Male figure wearing large light colored hat, front view, goatee, hair long to ears, wearing plaid bow tie, white shirt, black coat.
  - Unidentified Female Brinkerhoff-McNulty Family Member or Friend (Item 1-3)
    Female figure (bust) wearing large hat with feathers and dark scarf
  - Col. Webb (Item 1-4)
    Male figure, front view, wearing white shirt and collar, black bow-tie, black jacket, dark vest, hair parted on side, clean shaven.
    22. Col. Webb. verso.
  - Mrs. Thomas Shanklin (Emily Johnson) (Item 1-5)
    Female figure, front view, wearing white jumper and collar, brooch.
    Sitter is "mother of Emmons Johnson Gardner, father of Albert Ten Eyck Gardner."
  - Dr. J. D. Jones (Item 1-6)
    Male figure, front view, bearded, wearing white shirt with high white collar and bow tie.
  - Unidentified Female Greenwood Family Member or Friend [Mayer, J. S.], [ca1850-1860s] (Item 1-7)
    Female figure, front view, hair parted in middle, wearing earrings and brooch with dark blouse.
  - Mrs. Peter Kellogg (Julia B. Snow) (Item 1-9)
    Female figure wearing white lace collar and brooch, dark dress with black shawl, hair parted in middle and pulled back.
  - Margie Troughton Bradley (Item 1-10)
    Female figure (bust) wearing large black bow at neck, patterned blouse, headpiece/hat.
    Sitter is sister of Charles W. Troughton.
  - Unidentified Young Male (Item 1-11)
    Young boy seated wearing checked coat with ruffles at sleeves, white shirt underneath, white collar, dark pants, hair with large curl in front.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-12)
    Female figure, bust, front view, wearing choker necklace, plaid dress with black shoulder covering, hair parted in middle with braid across top.
  - Unidentified Male (Item 1-13)
    Male figure, front view, wearing black jacket and bow tie, white shirt and collar, hair curly, clean-shaven.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-14)
    Female figure, front view, 1/4 length, wearing plaid dress with v-neck collar, hair parted in middle and pulled back in snood.
  - Charlotte Isabel Peck (Item 1-15)
    Young girl seated wearing plaid off the shoulder dress with black jumper straps, cross necklace, bracelet.
  - Unidentified Male (Item 1-16)
    Male figure, front view, wearing dark jacket and pants with black vest and bow tie, white shirt, kerchief in pocket, straw hat, his left hand holding back of chair, right hand on lap holding flowers.
  - Unidentified Young Male (Item 1-17)
    Young boy wearing striped tie, white shirt, black vest and coat, hair light colored and parted on side, front view, 1/4 length.
  - Unidentified Young Male (Item 1-18)
    Young male figure, front view, wearing black bow tie and jacket, white shirt, hair parted on side.
  - Unidentified Young Female (Item 1-19)
    Female figure, front view, wearing plaid dress with white lining and collar, short necklace, hair parted in middle and short to just below ears, seated with her left arm resting on table, light colored eyes.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-20)
    Female figure wearing white collar, white cuffs, brooch, chain hanging from brooch, earrings, hair parted in middle, front view, hands on lap, white under-dress with black translucent overdress.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-21)
    Female figure, front view, wearing black dress with white collar and cuffs, hair parted in middle, brooch, snood, plaid lining on dress.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-22)
    Female figure seated wearing patterned dress with black lining and stripes, brooch, white collar, hair parted in middle, hands on lap.
  - Unidentified Infant [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 1-23)
    Infant seated, front view, wearing white gown, wrapped in dark blanket with checked lining, backdrop (?) of church interior.
  - Unidentified Female [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 1-24)
    Female figure, seated, wearing patterned dress with thin white collar, hair parted in middle.
  - Unidentified Young Female [Cathan, L.], [1843-1850] (Item 1-25)
    silhouette of young female figure wearing necklace, earrings, hair parted in middle, off the shoulder dress.
  - Thomas Soden Henry (Item 1-26)
    Male figure (bust), front view, wearing white collar and long sideburns; ambrotype of miniature?
    Sitter was born in Sligo, Ireland.
  - Clarina Bartow Shumway (Mrs. Charles Stedman Hanks), 1858/00/00 (Item 1-27)
    Infant (5 months old), front view, wearing bracelets on both wrists and white gown.
    Sitter is mother of donor and wife of Charles Stedman Hanks.
  - Unidentified Male [Geo. E. Mitchell's Gallery of Art] (Item 1-28)
    Male figure seated, front view, wearing black coat, his legs crossed and his right arm resting on table with book, bearded, hair parted on side, backdrop of buildings or fort.
  - Augustus Van Horne Stuyvesant Sr. (Item 1-29)
    Male figure, profile, wearing dark jacket and white collar, moustache.
  - Caroline Todd (Item 1-30)
    Female figure, front view, half-length, wearing bonnet, red sash under chin, coat buttoned up to chin.
  - Unidentified Young Male and 2 Unidentified Young Females Webb Family Members or Friends (2 Images) (Item 1-31)
    #1: Young Female figure seated wearing fur coat, white hat, young boy leaning against her (standing) wearing striped blouse; #2: Young female figure wearing brooch, ring, necklace, bracelet, hair parted in middle, patterned dark dress, thin white collar,
  - Unidentified Male Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-32)
    Male figure in profile, bearded, sideburns, dark jacket.
  - Unidentified Male Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-33)
    Male figure wearing large striped bow tie, black jacket, white shirt, bearded.
  - Unidentified Male Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-34)
    Male figure wearing dark coat with velvet collar, white shirt, bow tie, patterned vest, hair parted on side.
  - Unidentified Male Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-35)
    Male figure wearing goatee, black bow tie and coat, white shirt with black buttons.
  - Unidentified Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-36)
    Female figure wearing earrings, brooch, necklace, white lace collar, dark dress, bow in hair, hair parted in middle.
  - Unidentified Young Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-37)
    Female figure seated wearing bow in hair, black blouse (short scalloped sleeves), light colored skirt, white collar, hands on lap.
  - Unidentified Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-38)
    Female figure wearing large bow at neck (light with black trim), hat, gray coat, white collar, pin on coat.
  - Unidentified Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-39)
    Female figure seated wearing light colored dress that appears to be patterned, holding book?, hair parted in middle.
  - Unidentified Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-40)
    Female figure wearing plaid dress with white lace collar and brooch, thick bow in hair, shawl.
  - Unidentified Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-41)
    Female figure wearing long string around neck, light colored dress with plain white collar, bow in hair.
  - Unidentified Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-42)
    Female figure facing 1/4 to her right, wearing dark dress with plain white collar, hair short and parted in middle, white background.
  - Unidentified Young Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-43)
    Female figure turned 1/4 to her left, wearing brooch, hair in curls past shoulders and parted in middle, dark dress with plaid trim.
  - Unidentified Young Female Webb Family Member or Friend (Item 1-44)
    Young girl seated with her right arm resting on back of chair, bow in hair, white collar, dark dress, left hand on lap.
  - Elizabeth Brewster Comstock (Mrs. Peter Comstock) [Gates,] (Item 1-45)
    Female figure seated wearing white bonnet with ties in bow at neck, black dress, hands clasped on lap, her right elbow resting on table.
    Sitter is second wife of Peter Comstock.
  - George T. Bliss (Item 1-46)
    Young boy, half length, seated and wearing white lace collar and shirt (crocheting), and dark jacket.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-47)
    Female figure, front view, wearing polka dot dress with brooch, hair parted in middle, hands folded on lap, wearing belt.
  - Jacob Lindley Pyle (Item 1-48)
    Young boy, front view, resting temple on left hand, left elbow on table, white collar, bow tie, one-button jacket.
  - Unidentified Male Turner Family Member or Friend (Item 1-49)
    Male figure, seated with right arm resting on table, wearing thin moustache, white shirt, black bow tie, chain in vest.
  - Mary E. Comstock [Gates,], 1859/00/00 (Item 1-50)
    Female figure, front view, wearing earrings, hair parted in middle, white scalloped collar, brooch, black dress.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-51)
    Female figure seated, front view, wearing black dress with three large buttons down front, white collar and cuffs, earrings, snood, ring, hands on lap, holding feathered hat with left hand.
  - Unidentified Young Male (Item 1-52)
    Young boy standing wearing plaid shirt with white collar, his right arm resting on table, left hand at waist, curly hair parted on side and long to above ears, front view, half-length.
  - Unidentified Female (Item 1-53)
    Female figure, front view, wearing white dress with dark belt, choker necklace, earrings, ring, hair parted in middle, holding flowers (?) on lap.
  - Gertrude Kellogg (Item 1-54)
    Female figure seated wearing light colored dress with buttons down middle and sides, white collar, brooch, belt, cufflink, hair parted in middle and pulled back.
  - Gertrude Kellogg, 1860/00/00 (Item 1-55)
    Female figure 1/4 profile view, seated, wearing check dress and brooch with white collar, hair parted in middle and pulled back, belt on dress.
  - Peter Comstock [Gates,] (Item 1-56)
    Male figure, front view, wearing light gray coat and vest with white shirt, black tie, hair parted on side with curl over ear, arms crossed on stomach.
  - Unidentified Female [Holmes, Booth and Hayden] (Item 1-57)
    Female figure wearing glasses, holding what appears to be a book or Daguerreotype case in her left hand, wearing white bonnet, black cape and dress with black bow at neck.
  - Jane Bennett Thursby or Unidentified Female Thursby Family Member or Friend (Item 1-58)
    Female figure, front view, wearing bonnet with long sash tied under the chin and hanging down to waist, hands on lap, fur stole?, gloves?.
    Written on case: "Emma Thursby Collection".
  - Elizabeth Laurance (post-mortem) (Item 1-59)
    Female figure, profile view, post-mortem, white shroud covering head and shoulders, eyes closed, wrinkled face.
  - Phoebus, 1858/00/00 ca. (Item 1-60)
    Young boy seated with his right hand on hip and left arm resting on back of chair, wearing black jacket with bow tie, white shirt, dark pants, hair parted on side.
  - Unidentified Male (Item 1-61)
    Male figure, front view, wearing striped bow tie, white shirt, light colored vest, black jacket, clean shaven, bust.
  - Jane Bennett Thursby (Item 1-62)
    Female figure, front view, half length, wearing bonnet with sash tied under chin, cape with fringe on edge.
  - Unidentified Young Male [Holmes, S. A. (Silas A.), 1819 or 20-1886], [1847-ca1858] (Item 1-63)
    Young male figure wearing black jacket and bow tie, white shirt, checked pants, hair parted on side, ribbon around neck.
  - George Arcularius Unidentified Male Harper Family Member or Friend (Item 1-64)
    Male figure, seated, front view, with right arm on table, left hand on lap, dark jacket, white shirt and collar, clean-shaven, box? on table.
  - Andrew Arcularius or Unidentified Male Harper Family Member or Friend (Item 1-65)
    Older male figure, front view, clean shaven, wearing white shirt and collar, black bow tie.
  - Gertrude Kellogg, 1860/00/00 (Item 1-66)
  - Unidentified Young Female [Omlinson] (Item 1-67)
    Young girl, front view, wearing checked off the shoulder dress with light colored cap, brooch, hair parted in middle with bow in back.
  - Unidentified Young Female Greenwood Family Member or Friend (Item 1-68)
    Young girl, seated with hands on lap, front view, ribbons in hair, wearing locket, dark dress with plaid sleeves.
  - Unidentified Male James Family Member or Friend (Item 1-69)